Guide to the Percy E. Ryberg papers, 1906-1991 RL.01127
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Percy E. Ryberg papers
1906-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ryberg, Percy E. (Percy Edward), 1908-2001
RL.01127
6 Linear Feet 11 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Collection primarily comprises New York psychiatrist Percy E. Ryberg's personal family correspondence (in particular with his wife, Barbara), diaries, and other personal papers, some of which speak to Ryberg's youth in Argentina. Professional correspondence, articles, and other items document his career and interests in sexual and mental health, substance abuse treatments, identity, spiritual and astrological aspects of medicine, and other topics, and the publication of his book, Health, Sex, and Birth Control. Also includes biographical and genealogical information; photographs and photograph albums; and glass plate negatives. Acquired by the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Biographical Note
Percy Edward Ryberg (February 26, 1908-December 16, 2001) was a New York-based psychiatrist whose work focused on the treatment of alcoholism, mental health, gender identity, and sexual health. He was also interested in spiritual and astrological aspects of healing. He served as the president of the American Society of Addiction Medicine from 1965-1967. He was married to Barbara "Bobbie" Ryberg (January 18, 1912-October 1, 2003) of Baltimore, Maryland.
Access Restrictions
Portions of the collection are restricted. Portions of the Medical Research Materials are restricted for 100 years. Glass plate negatives are also closed to use; digital scans may be made. Contact the History of Medicine curator for permission to use these materials at least four weeks in advance of your visit.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Percy E. Ryberg papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2003.
Collection Overview
The collection consists primarily of psychiatrist Percy Ryberg's personal correspondence (in particular with his wife, Barbara), diaries, and other personal papers (1908-1991), some of which speak to his youth in Argentina. Ryberg's career as a physician and psychiatrist is represented through professional correspondence, writings, and medical research material. The material includes articles on the treatment of alcoholism in the mid-twentieth century, the publication of his book Health, Sex and Birth Control, and research on histamine reactions on the skin. Other topics that may be mentioned in the papers include mental health treatment, gender identity, schizophrenia, and spiritual and astrological aspects of medicine. There are also clippings and correspondence relating to the trial of William Koch (1940s), a U.S. physician who claimed to have developed a cure for cancer.
The collection also includes photographs (1906-1990s), mostly family snapshots and professional portraits of Ryberg, and photograph albums documenting Ryberg's travels and career. Glass plate negatives bear images of diplomas, and a military portrait of Ryberg from 1942.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Alcoholism -- Treatment; Astrology -- Therapeutic use; Identity (Psychology); Mental illness -- Treatment -- United States; Mental health; Psychiatrists -- Correspondence; Psychiatrists -- Diaries; Psychiatry -- History; Sexual health -- United States; Spiritual healing; Substance abuse -- Treatment; Argentina -- History; New York (N.Y.); Diaries; Glass plate negatives; Photograph albums; Photographs; Ryberg, Percy E. (Percy Edward), 1908-2001
- Genealogy, undated
  - Biographical sketch, 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Family tree and notes (Box 1, Folder Oversize Folder 1)
  - Descendants of Joseph and Ann Taylor (Box 1)
  - Taylor memoirs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1987 (Box 1)
  - Printed material, clippings (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
- Professional Activities, 1910s-1960s?
  - Citizenship, national residency, birth records (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae and professional profile (Box 1)
  - Announcements and events (Box 1)
  - Forms and applications (Box 1)
  - Certifications, memberships, diplomas (Box 1, Folder Oversize Folder 1)
  - Awards, honors (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1918-1991
  - General Correspondence, 1
    - 1918-1929 (Box 2)
    - 1930-1939 (Box 2)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 2)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1991 and undated (Box 2)
    - Insurance, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Professional Correspondence, 2
    - 1937-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1991 (Box 2)
    - Printed material from professional correspondence (Box 2)
- William Koch Trial, 1938-1943
  - Correspondence, 1938-1943 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1943 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Writings by Others, 3
    - "Alcoholismo y medicina pscicomatica" by Dr. Jamie Braver, 1985 and "A Social Perception of Freedom" by Dr. Hector Fontarosa, 1985, undated (Box 3)
  - Seminar on Alcoholism for Social Workers at Bronx Lebanon Hospital, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence regarding establishment of weekly column, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence regarding publication of Health, Sex, and Birth Control, 1948-1955 (Box 3)
  - Drafts, "A Combined Hospital Setting and AA in the Treatment of Alcoholism", 1968-1971 (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Spanish translations
  - Correspondence regarding "A Combined Hospital Setting and AA in the Treatment of Alcoholism", 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - Drafts, "A Medically Oriented Program for Handling Alcoholism in the City of New York" and "Report on Some Aspects of Alcoholism in England", October 1963, undated (Box 3)
  - Drafts, "Lecture on Venereal Disease", undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous drafts (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 3)
- Medical Research Material
  Conditions Governing Access
  Portions of the Medical Research Materials are restricted for 100 years. Contact the History of Medicine curator for permission to use these materials at least four weeks in advance of your visit.
  - "Observations on Histamine Skin Reactions Before and Following Administration of Histamine and Antihistamine " (Box 4)
  - Observations on histamine skin flares (Box 4)
    This material is restricted for 100 years. Contact the History of Medicine curator for permission to use these materials at least four weeks in advance of your visit.
  - Skin tests of histamines, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Patient charts (Box 4)
  - Treatment notes (Box 4)
  - Notes (Box 4)
  - Dr. Carl H Hannssen affidavit (Box 4)
  - Printed material (Box 4)
- Diaries
  - 1925 (Box 5)
  - February 1926-April 1926, photocopy (Box 5)
  - July 1926-October 1926 (Box 5)
  - October 1926-December 1926 (Box 5)
  - December 1926-March 1927 (Box 5)
  - March 1927-June 1927 (Box 5)
  - 1937 (Box 5)
  - 1938 (Box 5)
  - 1963 (Box 6)
  - 1965 (Box 6)
  - 1979 (Box 6)
  - 1990, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Address book (Box 6)
- Printed Material
  - Travel ephemera (Box 6)
  - Clippings and photocopies (Box 6)
  - Al Servico del País, 1902-1952 (Box 6)
    Materials in Spanish. Includes Ryber's thoughts on sexual education as a teenager.
  - Life-Giving Light by Charles Sheard, 1933 (Box 7)
  - Events (Box 7)
  - Clippings (Box 7)
    Includes materials in Spanish
- Photographs
  - Portraits of Percy Ryberg, undated (Box 7)
  - From professional activities, 1934, 1971, 1983, undated (Box 7, Oversize-folder 2)
  - Family portraits, 1906-1913 and undated (Box 7)
  - Wedding snapshots, Portrait of Barbara "Bobbie" Ryberg, undated (Box 7)
  - Snapshots of Percy Ryberg, 1969, 1986, 1987, and undated (Box 7)
  - Family snapshots, 1967-1991 and undated (Box 7)
  - Snapshots, people (Box 7)
  - Snapshots, landscapes (Box 7)
  - Negatives, copies of certificates, 1941 (Box 7)
  - Photograph album, undated (Box 7)
  - Photograph album, undated (Box 7)
  - Photograph album (Box 8)
  - Photograph album (Box 8)
  - Photograph album, Travel in Germany and United Kingdom, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Family Portraits, oversize, 1946, undated (Box 8)
  - Photograph album (Box 9)
  - Glass plate negatives (Box 10, Box 11)
    Glass negatives bear images of Ryberg's diplomas and a military portrait of Ryberg from 1942. Portrait has received treatment from Conservation.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Because glass plates are fragile and vulnerable, digital surrogates are preferred for research access. Please contact the Rubenstein staff before coming to use these materials.